<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before the Honourable House of Commons at St. Margarets Westminster, on Wednesday the 5th of April, 1699 being a solemn day of fasting for imploring a blessing on His Majesty and all his dominions, and for averting those judgments we most justly deserve, and for the distressed Protestants abroad  / by James Smalwood ...</title>
            <author>Smalwood, James, d. 1719.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 41 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60388</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4009</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10065</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13773260</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13773260</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101753</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60388)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101753)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 850:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before the Honourable House of Commons at St. Margarets Westminster, on Wednesday the 5th of April, 1699 being a solemn day of fasting for imploring a blessing on His Majesty and all his dominions, and for averting those judgments we most justly deserve, and for the distressed Protestants abroad  / by James Smalwood ...</title>
                  <author>Smalwood, James, d. 1719.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 23, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Abel Roper ad R. Basset ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title: A fast-sermon before the House of Commons.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms LXXX, 19 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Fast-day sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:101753:1"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Jovis 6 die Aprilis</hi> 1699.</head>
            <p>ORdered, That the thanks of this Houſe be given to Mr. <hi>Smal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood,</hi> for the Sermon by him Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before them Yeſterday, at St. <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garet</hi>'s <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and that he be deſired to Print the ſame, and that Mr. <hi>Gerrard</hi> and Colonel <hi>Mounta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue</hi> do acquaint him therewith.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Paul Jodrell <hi>Cl' Dom' Com'.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101753:1"/>
            <p> A SERMON Preached before the Honourable <hi>Houſe of Commons.</hi> AT St. Margarets Weſtminſter, On <hi>Wedneſday</hi> the <hi>5th</hi> of <hi>April,</hi> 1699.</p>
            <p>Being a ſolemn day of Faſting for <hi>Imploring a Bleſſing on his Majeſty, and all his Dominions, and for averting thoſe Judgments we moſt juſtly deſerve, and for the diſtreſſed Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants abroad.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>James Smalwood,</hi> Chaplain to the Right Honourable the Earl of <hi>Romney,</hi> and His Majeſties own Regiment of Foot-Guards.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Abel Roper,</hi> and <hi>R. Baſset,</hi> in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet.</hi> 1699.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:101753:2"/>
            <p> Mr. <hi>SMALWOOD</hi>'s FAST-SERMON Before the Houſe of COMMONS. April 5. 1699.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:101753:3"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:101753:3"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:101753:4"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:101753:4"/>
            <head>A FAST-SERMON BEFORE THE <hi>Houſe of Commons.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>PSAL. 80. laſt ver.</bibl>
               <q>Turn us again, O Lord God of Hoſts, ſhew us the light of thy countenance and we ſhall be whole.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IF we read over this whole Pſalm, we may plainly diſcover by it, that the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were, when it was compoſed, under ſome great and heavy affliction, <hi>Thou feedeſt us with the bread of tears, ond thou giveſt us plenteouſneſs of tears to drink; Thou haſt made us a very ſtrife unto</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:101753:5"/> 
               <hi>our neighbours, and our enemies laugh us to ſcorn,</hi> ſays the Pſalmiſt, v. 5. and 6. whereupon according to his uſual cuſtom he addreſſes himſelf to Almighty God for Relief and Succour, <hi>Hear O thou ſhepheard of Iſrael,</hi> ſays he, v. 1. <hi>ſtir up thy ſtrength and come help and us,</hi> verſe 2. <hi>How long wilt thou be angry with thy people that pray,</hi> verſ. 4. and to mention no more of his pathetical Supplications, no leſs than three times in this ſhort Pſalm, which adds extremely not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the fervency, but alſo to the Beauty and Harmony of his Prayer, he repeats the words I have choſe for my Text, <hi>Turn us again, O Lord God of Hoſts, ſhew us the light of thy countenance, and we ſhall be whole,</hi> or as the old Tranſlation ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders it nearer the Hebrew, <hi>Turn us again, O Lord God of Hoſts, cauſe thy face to ſhine upon us, and we ſhall be ſaved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now though the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s caſe at that time, and ours at preſent is not altogether the ſame, tho (bleſſed be God) we of this Nation do not now labour under any publick affliction, neither have our Enemies any great reaſon to <hi>laugh us to ſcorn;</hi> yet to ſhew that this Pſalm is very ſuitable to the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of our preſent meeting, we may obſerve the Holy Prophet prays particularly for <hi>three</hi> things in it, wherein we may reaſonably ſuppoſe he judged the welfare of the people to conſiſt, and which three things we are by publick Authority enjoyned this day to pray to God for.</p>
            <p>1. He prays for a Bleſſing upon the King, <hi>let thy hand be upon the man of thy right hand, and upon the Son of Man, whom thou haſt made ſo ſtrong for thine own ſelf.</hi> v. 17.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:101753:5"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>2dly.</hi> He prays for the afflicted condition of the Church, That <hi>God in his great meroy and goodneſs would relieve and comfort</hi> that, and this he couches very elegantly under the Metapher of a vine, <hi>Thou haſt brought a vine out of Aegypt, thou haſt caſt out the heathen and planted it, thou madeſt room for it, and when it had taken root it filled the land, why haſt thou then broken down her hedge, that all thoſe that go by pluck off her grapes, the wild boar out of the wood does root it up, and the wild beasts of the field devour it.</hi> verſ. 12. 13.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>3dly.</hi> He prays to God to remove and <hi>avert thoſe judgements which the manifold ſins and provocations of the people had juſtly deſerved,</hi> and that is implyed in the words of my Text.</p>
            <p>Theſe <hi>three</hi> things the Holy Prophet particularizes in this Pſalm, exactly agreeable to the duty required of us this day: But what he chiefly ſues for, and lays the ſtreſs of his Prayers on, as a means of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing the other two, and indeed all Bleſſings what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, is a general converſion and repentance of the people; this is his chiefeſt aim, this we find the main ſcope and burden of this his heavenly Song, therefore it is he repeats theſe words ſo often, and heigthens them ſtill with greater vehemency and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour every time than other; <hi>Turn us again O God,</hi> verſ. 3. <hi>Turn us again O Lord God,</hi> verſ. 7. <hi>Turn us again O Lord God of hoſts, ſhew us the light of thy coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance and we ſhall be whole.</hi> verſ. 19.</p>
            <p>The words are of themſelves very plain and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligible, not to ſpend therefore any time in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planation of them. From the conſideration of the circumſtances which King <hi>David</hi> and his people were
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:101753:6"/> now in, which was under the Judgments of God, and the methods that he took to remove thoſe judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which was a general converſion of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple from ſin, I draw theſe two doctrinal conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In reſpect to God, that the chief end and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign God aims at in ſending judgments upon a People or Nation, is to reclaim them from their ſins.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In reſpect to Men, that the only way a People or Nation has to avert God's judgments, is to turn from their ſins.</p>
            <p>I ſhall ſpeak to theſe two Points, and then apply them to the buſineſs of the day.</p>
            <p>1. The chief end and deſign God aims at in ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Judgments on a People is to reclaim them from their ſins. It may here be ſaid, that the end of all the diſpenſations of God to mankind is to convert them from ſin: For this very purpoſe did he ſend his Son into the World, to draw and win us to himſelf, by the promiſes of Heaven and Eternal Happineſs, and all the attractive motives that can be ſuppos'd to work upon Humane underſtanding, and for this only reaſon does God daily beſtow his mercies and benefits upon us; according to what St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us, <hi>The goodneſs of God leadeth us to Repentance,</hi> Rom. 2. 4. Why then if the gentler methods of lenity and mercy may have the ſame effect, does God uſe the ſeverer ways of reclaiming men by pouring Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Afflictions upon them?</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:101753:6"/>
            <p> To this I anſwer, The ways which God chiefly delights to deal with mankind in, are gentleneſs, <note place="margin">Rom. 2. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Goodneſs, Forbearance and Long-ſuffering, God does not</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Lam. 3. 33.</note> 
               <hi>afflict willingly nor grieve the Children of Men,</hi> ſays the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> nay, the whole tenour of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture diſcovers this to be the nature of God; and were it not that we are ſuch perverſe Creatures as not to be wrought upon by kindneſs, ſo wild as not to be tamed by gentle uſage, God would not handle us in any other way, <hi>I drew them with the cords of a Man, with the bands of Love,</hi> ſays the Holy ſpirit in the Prophet <hi>Hoſea,</hi> but the <hi>Jews</hi> but ſtill ſo ſtiff-necked and untractable they would not follow, ſo that <note place="margin">v. 11. 4.</note> they almoſt forced God, contrary to his inclination, to take the rod into his hand, and when they would not lead then to drive them, God was forc'd to turn thoſe ſoft cords into whips, and thoſe bands of Love into ſhackels of Iron.</p>
            <p>And yet when God comes to take this courſe with Man, he ſtill, like a prudent Parent, aims at nothing but his good and benefit by it, if he puts a yoke upon our necks, it is but to breing us to humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, if he puts the bitt into our mouths, it is but to check our career in ſin, if he afflicts us, it is not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is pleaſant to him to deal harſhly with us, but becauſe it is profitable and neceſſary for us ſo to be dealt with.</p>
            <p>This the holy Scripture informs us to be the end of all the ſevere methods of Providence towards the Sons of Men, this, <hi>Moſes</hi> tells us, made God exerciſe the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> with all the hardſhips could be inflicted on them for forty years in the Wilderneſs, <hi>He led thee through that great and terrible Wilderneſs</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:101753:7"/> 
               <hi>wherein were fiery Serpents, and Scorpions, that he might humble thee, and that he might prove thee, to do thee good at the latter end,</hi> Deut. 8. 15. So that the afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Providences of God are not only apt in their own nature to do us good: but, which is a great argument of his goodneſs, God intends and aims at this end a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone by them. Indeed we often read in Scripture of God's <hi>Anger</hi> and <hi>Wrath,</hi> and <hi>heavy diſpleaſure,</hi> and <hi>Fury</hi> and <hi>Indignation,</hi> but it is always againſt Mens ſins and not their perſons; and if his reſentments are ſo great as to provoke him to inflict any Judgment, yet ſtill it is with a merciful deſign in the end. If he has viſited a Nation with any Plague, or ſore Diſeaſe, it was only to let out its corruption, if he has thrown us into the <hi>Furnace of affliction, and try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us ſo as by Fire,</hi> it was that he might refine and purifie us from the droſs of our Sins; If he has em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baraſs'd us in War and Battle, it was only to let out ſo much hot blood, that the whole body might be the more cool and temperate, and healthful after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards; ſo that, tho' it cannot be denied but that the Judgments of God are evil in themſelves, yet conſidering the intention of them, they are no real objections againſt the mercy and goodneſs of God, but rather Arguments for it.</p>
            <p>My firſt Doctrinal concluſion appearing thus evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, namely, That the chief end and deſign which God aims at by ſending his Judgments upon a Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, is to turn them from their Sins, that ſo they may be ſaved; what follows but that we make the right uſe of this Doctrine. If Judgments which are in themſelves very irkſome and grievous to humane nature, muſt be the remedies of ſin, why will we not live regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:101753:7"/> and prevent them? What corrupt humours are to the body, that ſin is to the ſoul, its greateſt Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe and Malignity; now if we will contract ill hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours and diſtempers, if we will make our ſelves ſick, that is our own miſmanagement and ſolly, and no fault of the Phyſitian, but if when we are ſick the Phyſitian does recover us, tho' it be by the moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſant and bittereſt draughts, we are moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly beholden to him; all Temporal and Worldly Judgments are properly medicinal, and if we will but ſuffer them to have their kindly operation up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us, they will work our cure, and how grievous and diſtaſtful ſoever they may ſeem for the preſent, they will prove mercies and bleſſings in the end, for this reaſon Holy <hi>David</hi> reckons afflictions amongſt the bleſſings of his Life, <hi>It is good for me,</hi> ſays he, <note place="margin">Pſal. 119. 72.</note> 
               <hi>that I have been afflicted:</hi> And he gives the reaſon for it in the ſame <hi>Pſalm, Before I was afflicted I went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stray, but now I have learnt thy precepts;</hi> But howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, altho' <hi>David</hi> did make the right uſe of his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, altho' he applied what God adminiſtred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, and it wrought its intended cure upon him, yet ſtill that Man muſt be allowed to have lived moſt cautiouſly who the leaſt wants ſuch ſharp Phyſick; He certainly muſt be judged to take a greater care of his health, who by a Temperate diet and Regular way of living prevents ſickneſs, than he that ſuffers a malady to grow upon him, and to corrupt the whole maſs of his blood, ſo that nothing at laſt but the moſt violent courſes, and the moſt painful applications can reſtore him to his former health. And this brings me to my other doctrinal concluſion from the Text, which this.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:101753:8"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>2dly.</hi> That the only way a Nation or a People has to avert God's Judgments, is to forſake their ſins.</p>
            <p>The Chriſtian Religion as it preſcribes the beſt and moſt reaſonable precepts of any Religion that ever was in the World for the peace and happineſs of every private Man; ſo likewiſe does it afford the moſt expedient rules for the ſafety and preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of Publick Communities; converſion from Sin, and Repentance, Mortification of our Luſts and Appetites, by Watchings, Faſtings, and Prayers, and the humiliation of our Bodies, in order to raiſe in our Souls good and devout thoughts, are duties re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired from all of us by our Holy Religion, and tho theſe duties may be ſaid to tend moſt directly to the reformation and amendment of ſingle perſons, yet becauſe the whole conſiſts of its parts, the compounded Body of a Nation muſt find a benefit from the good which accrews to the ſeveral members of it; and therefore it is King <hi>Soloman</hi> ſays that <hi>righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs exalteth a nation.</hi> The practice of Vertue and Piety begets a Reverence and Honour, a Reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and a worldly Glory to any people; but on the contrary, be a Country never ſo exalted by Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion and Power, and Wealth, and all other tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral advantages, and wanting at the ſame time in the moral accompliſhments of Vertue and Juſtice and Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, that Country will by degrees grow baſe and contemptible, and in the end be ruined, for the ſame Wiſe man tells us, <hi>ſin is the reproach of any people,</hi> and this will appear to be true from two cauſes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> From the nature of the thing it ſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> From the Judgments of God.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:101753:8"/>
            <p> 1. From the nature of the thing it ſelf: Whatever Nation degenerates in its Manners, muſt decay gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dually in its Power and Strength, and conſequently, is in a ready way to Ruin. Sin, of what kind ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, is againſt the Intereſt of a People: Lewdneſs and Intemperance, and ſuch like Vices, debaſe Men's Courage and Spirit; they breed Infirmities and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, which ſpoil the Strain of a Nation, and then it becomes languid, feeble and cowardly, and at laſt muſt be the Scorn, as well as the Triumph, of its Enemies. Irreligion, Profaneneſs and Atheiſm quite unhinge a Government; for where there is no Belief of a God, there are no Hopes or Fears of future Rewards or Puniſhments: And when you are once come to that, what can hinder all manner of Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs from breaking in upon you? Falſhood and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice, Perſidiouſneſs and Treachery, Theft, Rapine and Murther, and all the Black Crew of Villainies, muſt burſt in where the Barrier of Religion is bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken down: And whenever ſuch a Flood as this pours in upon a Nation, what can hinder it from being ruin'd, either by others, or it ſelf?</p>
            <p>2. It is not only that the Nature of the State it ſelf will bring Ruin on a wicked People, but God's Judgments will likewiſe fall upon them. Inded, as to private Perſons, the Caſe is not the ſame; for God is ſometimes pleas'd to let good Men live mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerably, and the Wicked to proſper in this World; but there is a very good Reaſon for it, becauſe he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves the Rewarding of the one, and the Puniſhing of the other, till a more convenient Seaſon of Retri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution. But God does not deal after the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner with Nations, becauſe publick Bodies and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munities
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:101753:9"/> of Men, as ſuch, can only be rewarded and puniſh'd in this World: In the World to come, all Corporations and Societies will be quite diſſolv'd; God will not then reward or puniſh Nations, as Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; but every Man muſt give an Account of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and accordingly receive his own Perſonal Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence: Therefore the general Sins of a Nation can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not eſcape God's Judgments here upon Earth, unleſs they be prevented by a National Repentance.</p>
            <p>And indeed, all along the Hiſtory of the <hi>Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament,</hi> we find this to be true by the different Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences of God always ſuited to the Manners of the <hi>Jews;</hi> they were conſtantly proſperous, or afflicted, according as Vertue or Vice reign'd amongſt them. Nor was it towards his own People alone that God uſed this conſtant Method; St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> tells us, That the mighty Succeſs and Greatneſs of the <hi>Romans</hi> was a Reward given them from Heaven, for their eminent Juſtice, Temperance, and other Vertues. And tho' we muſt not peremptorily conclude, that the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of God's Juſtice ſhall be the ſame to all Nations that it was to the People of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> yet thus much may be probably concluded from it, That as God always favour'd that People when they were obedient to him, and ſent his Judgments among them when they rebell'd againſt him; ſo he will alſo deal with other Nations; and this Concluſion is drawn from an Everlaſting and Unchangeable Cauſe; and that is, the Juſtice of the Divine Providence.</p>
            <p>This is what Religion and Reaſon teach us, That the only Way to procure God's Bleſſings, and avert his Judgments is, to work a thorow Reformation on our Lives: And it were to be wiſh'd that all Men
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:101753:9"/> were ſo well diſpos'd, that Religion by its Authority, and Reaſon by its Force, might be ſufficient to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh this Truth in the Minds of Men; but the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions of Humane Nature will always make a ſtrong Oppoſition againſt it; and the Degeneracy of the preſent Age in particular is ſo very great, that no Arguments drawn either from the invincible Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations of Religion, or the Light of Reaſon, ſeem to be ſufficient for it.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, at the firſt Planting of Chriſtianity, we find the great Author of it then complaining of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſibility of Men, that <hi>their Hearts were waxed groſs,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Matt. 13. 45.</note> 
               <hi>and their Ears were dull of hearing, and their Eyes were cloſed; leſt at any time they ſhould ſee with their Eyes, or hear with their Ears, or underſtand with their Hearts, and ſhould be converted, and he ſhould heal them:</hi> And therefore our Saviour then accompany'd his Doctrine with Miracles; and where he could not prevail with Words, there he convinc'd by Actions. But now it has pleaſed God to withdraw that Power, and has left his Church to be carry'd on and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported by more ordinary and Humane Ways, by the Succeſſion of the Miniſterial Function, by the Power of Preaching, and uſing all ſuch Arguments and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives to bring Men to their Duty, which the Holy Spirit has reveal'd to us, and deſign'd for theſe good Purpoſes: But this, we find, will not do; Paul <hi>may plant, and</hi> Apollos <hi>may water:</hi> The Miniſters of the Goſpel may uſe what Means they can to reclaim Men, but ſtill we ſee no viſible Effects of all their Labours; Men will not hearken to the Voice of theſe <hi>Charmers, charm they never ſo wiſely.</hi> We are <note place="margin">Pſal. 50. 5.</note> taught therefore, in this Caſe, to call in the Aſſiſtance
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:101753:10"/> of the Civil Power, and the Countenance of Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; we muſt apply to them who are our Governors, to them who St. <hi>Peter</hi> tells us <hi>are ſent by God, for the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2. 14.</note> 
               <hi>Puniſhment of Evil-doers, and for the Praiſe of thoſe that do well:</hi> Which, indeed, was never more neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to be done than in this preſent Age, which is prodigiouſly ſunk into Atheiſm and Profaneneſs, and conſequently into the foulleſt Immoralities, and the moſt Beſtial Vices whatever; Vices of ſuch a kind, that, tho', in Obedience to St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Direction, I ſhall not <hi>ſo much as once name them among you,</hi> yet the Remembrance of a late publick Example cannot hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der us from thinking of ſome of them.</p>
            <p>'Tis this Univerſal and Monſtrous Wickedneſs that has excited <hi>You,</hi> our wiſe Governors, to provide ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Laws that might be thought effectual for the ſuppreſſing of it; and, to mention no more, One, I think, if it were carefully put in Execution, would contribute much towards the ſuppreſſing of Atheiſm and Irreligion; and that is, <hi>The Act againſt the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts.</hi> That Looſneſs of Principles, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Libertiniſm of Living, which may be obſerv'd now to ſpread and grow upon us, may be imputed in great part to ſome Emiſſaries of <hi>Rome,</hi> who ſtill are (I ſpeak it knowingly) lurking among us: Theſe Men, by what Authority I know not, I am ſure not by his from whom they unworthily take their Name, aſſume to themſelves a peculiar Propriety of the Guidance of Men's Conſciences; they creep into all Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, and get poſſeſſion of as many Families as they can; and then, by their Arts and Inſinuations, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet and undermine the Principles of Men's Religion; and often-times, while they endeavour to bring a
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:101753:10"/> Man over to <hi>their</hi> Religion, they craftily ſteal away his own, and leave him without any. Popery, by its own very Tendency and Diſpoſition, muſt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dually lead Men into Atheiſm, Superſtition, and an Idolatrous Worſhip; ſet up many Gods, and then, as it is the Humour of Mankind to ſtart often-times from one Extream to another, rather than they will have ſo many impos'd upon them, they will chuſe to have none. Nay, if you trace Atheiſm to its Fountain-head, you will find it ſprings from the corrupt Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Court: <hi>Italy</hi> was the place where it chiefly reign'd for ſome time; our Anceſtors here in <hi>England,</hi> if Hiſtory may be credited, knew none of thoſe <hi>Italian</hi> Vices: But in this laſt Age, Atheiſm began to travel over the <hi>Alpes,</hi> and infected <hi>France;</hi> and now at laſt it has croſs'd the Seas, and has inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded our Nation, and (which is much to be lament<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) has prevail'd too in it.</p>
            <p>I have dwelt a little upon this Article, becauſe I think the only Way for this Nation to flouriſh and be happy, and for the Proteſtant Church to ſtand pure and uncorrupt, is, to remove, if poſſible, all thoſe far from it, whoſe Buſineſs and Study it is, not only to diſtract our Government, but alſo to pollute our Manners.</p>
            <p>But I leave this, next to God, to the Great and Wiſe Council of the Nation. I proceed now,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly.</hi> To apply what has been ſaid to the Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs of the Day. And becauſe we have heard, <hi>Firſt,</hi> That the chief Deſign of God's Judgments up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a People, is, to reclaim them from their Sins; and <hi>Secondly,</hi> That the only Way a People had to prevent and avert God's Judgments, was, to forſake their
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:101753:11"/> Sins; therefore Converſion from Sin, to God, muſt be eſteem'd a neceſſary Spiritual Duty: And tho' this Duty is moſt certainly always very requiſite and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, yet there are ſome Seaſons when the Church does moſt chiefly require it; and, to name no more, this preſent Seaſon is the greateſt; now in the Time of <hi>Lent,</hi> but more eſpecially in this <hi>Magna Hebdoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da,</hi> this <hi>Great Week</hi> before the Reſurrection, we are call'd upon to make a ſtrict Re-view of our Lives, and to humble our Souls in God's Preſence, and to bewail our manifold Tranſgreſſions, and to devote our ſelves afreſh to his Service. This Obligation the holy Church lays upon us: But ſtill there is another Engagement for our moſt ſolemn Humiliation on this Day, Publick Authority has added a further Injun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction on us: To anſwer therefore this double Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, and that we may perform the Office of the Day aright, let us enquire what we have now to do; and that I ſhall conſider of after this Two-fold Manner:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt, Generally;</hi> What <hi>all</hi> Days of Humiliation do require of us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly, Particularly;</hi> What <hi>this</hi> Day diſtinctly requires.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> All Days of Publick Humiliation ſeem to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire theſe Three Things at our Hands:</p>
            <p n="1">1. That we ſhould humble our ſelves before God, every one for his own Perſonal Sins, whereby he has provok'd God, and increas'd the publick Guilt, and done his part to bring down the Judgments and Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance of God upon the Nation.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That we ſhould likewiſe heartily lament the Sins of the Publick, eſpecially the great and crying
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:101753:11"/> Sins of the Nation, whereby the Wrath and Indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God has been ſo juſtly incens'd againſt us.</p>
            <p n="3">3. We ſhould proſecute this our Humiliation with an Actual Reformation and Amendment of our Lives for the future.</p>
            <p>I do but juſt mention theſe Particulars, without any Enlargement on them that I may more fully ſpeak to the Duties of the Day, which are theſe <hi>Three:</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. We are this Day to pray to God that he would <hi>avert thoſe Judgments which our manifold Sins and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations have moſt juſtly deſerv'd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That he would, <hi>in his great Mercy and Goodneſs, relieve and comfort ſuch as ſuffer abroad for the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. We are to <hi>implore a Bleſſing from Almighty God, upon His Majeſty, and all His Dominions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. We are to make our Supplications unto God for the <hi>Averting of thoſe Judgments which our manifold Sins and Provocations have juſtly deſerv'd.</hi> 'Tis true, we of this Nation have lately receiv'd no ſmall To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens of God's favourable Inclinations to us, in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowing upon us a Grateful and an Honourable Peace; a Peace that, I hope, may prove a competent Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence to us for all our Toils, and Fatigues, and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences: But if we continue to lead Lives unſuitable to ſuch Bleſſings receiv'd, how eaſily may God find a Way to let in the ſame Enemy afreſh upon us? King <hi>David</hi> tells us, That <hi>the Lord gives Strength un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his People; the Lord gives his People the Bleſſing of Peace:</hi> That is, God Almighty defends, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tects his People: but 'tis only ſo long as they are obedient to him; for he ſays in another place, <hi>If</hi> a
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:101753:12"/> 
               <hi>Man will not turn, God will whet his Sword, and will bend his Bow and make it ready, and prepare for him the Inſtruments of Death.</hi> God Almighty has dealt all along with this Nation, as he formerly did with his own peculiar People, the <hi>Jews:</hi> He has exerciſed, and made Trial of us, by all the wiſe Arts of his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Providence; we have felt the Powers both of his Mercy, and his Juſtice, Alternately: Out of his <hi>Mercy</hi> he would never deſtroy us quite, yet it has, as it were, puzzl'd his <hi>Juſtice</hi> how to ſave us: We read of four ſorts of Judgments wherewith God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly uſed to endeavour to reclaim the Antient <hi>Jews, Plague, Fire, Sword</hi> and <hi>Famine;</hi> we in this Nation have, in a few Years, felt the former <hi>Three;</hi> and, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, we have ſome Reaſon to fear, from the remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Defect and Decay of the Seaſons for ſome Years laſt paſt, that if we do not repent in time, and depre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>care God's heavy Diſpleaſure againſt us, his Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence may be a preparing the <hi>Fourth,</hi> and the moſt dreadful of them all, a <hi>Famine,</hi> for us.</p>
            <p>Let us therefore, with the greateſt Importunities, make our Addreſſes now to Almighty God, that he would be pleas'd to avert thoſe terrible Judgments which we ſo righteouſly have deſerv'd, and to which the great Sins of the Nation do now ſo juſtly expoſe us; humbly beſeeching him, not for us, but for his his own Name's ſake, and becauſe we are his People, and are called after his Name, and becauſe his holy Faith and Religion are profeſs'd among us, that he would be pleas'd to hear the Prayers and Supplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of his Servants, which they have made before him this Day. And, together with our ſelves, let us pray unto God, that he would pleaſe,</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:101753:12"/> 2. To regard our diſtreſſed Brethren in the Faith, all the World over; particularly, <hi>to relieve and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort thoſe that ſuffer abroad for the Proteſtant Religion.</hi> 'Tis a mighty Scandal to the Chriſtian Religion, and what all <hi>Jews, Turks</hi> and <hi>Pagans</hi> may juſtly reproach the Followers of <hi>Chriſt</hi> with, that there are ſuch im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placable Diviſions, and ſuch barbarous Perſecutions practis'd and kept up among us. The Doctrine of the great Author of our Faith was made up all of Love; this was the diſtinguiſhing Character his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples were to be known by, <hi>If they lov'd one another:</hi> Yet in a certain Church, and a Church too that boaſts it ſelf the only true Church of Chriſt, we find that Badge and Character quite worn off; for, inſtead of loving thoſe who cannot perſuade their Conſciences to ſwallow ſuch groſs Abſurdities as they do them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, theſe Men think they <hi>do God good Service if they kill them.</hi> I might produce many Inſtances of this outragious Zeal, againſt the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church; The cruel Inhumanities againſt the <hi>Vaudois,</hi> the But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheries of the <hi>Albigenſes</hi> and the Poor of <hi>Lyons,</hi> the total Extirpation of the Proteſtants in <hi>Moravia, Sile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia, Bohemia</hi> and <hi>Hungary,</hi> the Maſſacre of the <hi>Hugo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nots</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> and the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Proteſtants in <hi>Ireland;</hi> not to mention thoſe Ignominious Flames that were kindl'd in our own Queen <hi>Mary</hi>'s Days, and that terrible and unparallell'd Deſign that was laid to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the <hi>Lords and Commons</hi> of our Nation at one Blow in the ſucceeding Reign, are all Memorable Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of the Popiſh Cruelty. But we need not look back into Hiſtory to furniſh us with Inſtances of this kind; how many living Objects of our Compaſſion are ſtill under great Preſſures from them in the neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:101753:13"/> Countries to us! And how many Thouſands have fled from thence, to us, for Refuge? There, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, the <hi>Vine</hi> of the Lord does moſt apparently ſuffer; there <hi>the Wild-Boar of the Wood does root it up, and the Wild-Beaſts of the Field devour it.</hi> But let us, with King <hi>David,</hi> ſay, <hi>Turn thee again, O Lord God of Hoſts; look down from Heaven, behold and viſit this Vine, and the place of the Vineyard which thy Right Hand hath planted, and the Branch that thou madeſt ſo ſtrong for thine own ſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The Third Duty of the Day is, <hi>to implore a Bleſſing from Almighty God upon His Majeſty, and all his Dominions.</hi> And here I think it altogether un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary to uſe any Arguments to excite your Zeal, or to heighten your Affections; Intereſt, which is the firſt Spring and great Director of all our Actions, if not Gratitude, will recommend this Duty to us: The great Benefits and Advantages we have already receiv'd from him, are ſufficient Motives to pray for his long and happy Reign over us. He that has pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd our Rights and Liberties, that has reſcu'd our Religion, that has maintain'd our Laws, that has de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feated the Deſigns of our Enemies, that has ſubdu'd the Diſturbers of our Peace; he that has run all Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zards of his Life, often croſs'd the Seas, travers'd many Countries, ventur'd his Perſon in Battel, and ſometimes very narrowly ſav'd it; he that has oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and ſtemm'd too, the Tide of a Power generally thought irreſiſtible: In a Word, he that has ſettl'd us in Peace at home, and procur'd us Honour abroad; if he does not deſerve our hearty good Wiſhes, and moſt ſincere Prayers, I know not what Obligations can extort that Duty from us.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:101753:13"/>
            <p> The Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> is now in as hopeful a Condition as any Nation can be, if we are not want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in ſome Caſes to our ſelves: If we can preſerve our Peace with as much Prudence and Unanimity, as we carry'd on the War with Heartineſs and Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage; if we keep our Country as quiet within our ſelves, as we defended it bravely againſt others; in a Word, if we live up to the Rules of our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, as well as we fought for it; then will <hi>England,</hi> in time, not only recover its Strength and Riches, flouriſh and grow great within it ſelf, but it will be able to give Laws to all its Neighbours round about it: And, indeed, not to flatter our ſelves, there is no Kingdom I know of in the World ſo every way capable of being made Great and Glorious, as we are now at this time; and that upon theſe <hi>Two</hi> Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts:</p>
            <p n="1">1. We have a King, whom God ſeems to have brought into the World, to have train'd up and preſerv'd on purpoſe for us: A Man of our own Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and indeed, of a true <hi>Engliſh</hi> Temper and Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius; a Man skilful and courageous in War, wiſe and ſatisfy'd in Peace; a Man that repoſes a great Truſt in the Fidelity of his Subjects, and a Man in whom they may repoſe theirs; a Man ſo wholly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd for the Good of his People, that he is always ready to hearken to their Counſels, and to comply with them; a Man, in ſhort, altogether inclin'd, and every way qualify'd, both to ſerve, and to protect his People; a Man, to ſum up all, of whom I would not be thought to ſpeak too great a Thing, if I ſay he is as brave a Warrior as either <hi>Alexander</hi> or <hi>Caeſar</hi> was, becauſe I deſign to ſpeak yet a greater, and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:101753:14"/> that is, that he is as good a Chriſtian as either <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine</hi> or <hi>Theodoſius</hi> was.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We have a People, famous in the World for great Valour and Courage, always having had a good Skill in Arms, and of ſuch undaunted Spirits, that if we were united within our ſelves, we are able perhaps to grapple with the moſt potent Kingdoms near us. We are a happy Nation too in our Situa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: When the Prophet <hi>Ezekiel</hi> tells us of the Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs of <hi>Canaan,</hi> he deſcribes it to be <hi>a Land of Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wall'd</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 38. 11.</note> 
               <hi>Villages, where the People are at reſt, and dwell ſafely; all of them dwelling without Walls, and having neither Bars nor Gates:</hi> So we of this Nation have no need of Walling and Fortifying our Towns, as ſome of our Friends upon the Continent are forc'd to do; becauſe, as the Prophet <hi>Nahum</hi> ſpeaks of the City of <hi>No,</hi> we <hi>have the Sea for a Rampart to us.</hi> We are ſtill <note place="margin">Nah. 3. 8.</note> happier by our Conſtitution and Government, which, by its excellent Laws and Adminiſtration, ſo effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually provides for the Security, Quiet and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of the People, that of no Nation under Heaven may it be more properly ſaid, that <hi>every Man may ſit</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mic. 4 4.</note> 
               <hi>under his own Vine, and under his Fig-tree, and no Man ſhall make him afraid.</hi> And we are happieſt of all in our Church; a Church, which for Purity of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, Decency of Worſhip, and all Advantages for Piety, may compare with, if not exceed, any Church upon the Face of the Earth.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the peculiar Advantages of <hi>England,</hi> and theſe are the Happineſſes we at preſent enjoy; there is but one thing wanting to continue and ſecure theſe Bleſſings to us, and without that, all our Skill in Arms, all our Natural Courage, all our Plenty and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:101753:14"/> Security, our wholſome Laws, and wiſe Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, will not be able to ſupport and maintain us; and that is, True Godlineſs and Vertue. Let us all therefore pour out our moſt Affectionate Prayers un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, to aſſiſt us with his Grace in the Attainment of theſe Accompliſhments: And to his Grace, which he is never backward of affording us, let us add out own Endeavours; let us ſhew the good Effects of theſe our Days of Humiliation in all the other Days of our Life. What ſhall it profit us to depend upon our Mortification and Faſting, when God ſhall ſay, as he ſpeaks by the Prophet <hi>Zechary, Did you at all faſt unto me, even unto me?</hi> The proper Fruit of Faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is, to forſake our Sins, and become better for the future; without this, all our Faſting will but fill us with Wind, all our Tears will be but as Water ſpilt upon the Ground; in a Word, all our Penances will but create us Pain here, and increaſe it hereafter.</p>
            <p>But if we do now unfeignedly reſolve to amend for the future, and ſhall proſecute thoſe Reſolutions in the Series of our Lives, we may then hope that God will <hi>incline his Ear unto us, and hear:</hi> In ſure and certain Hopes of which, we now, according as we are appointed.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Pray, that God would bleſs, preſerve and keep our preſent King, as the Inſtrument by which he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf has choſe to work ſuch wondrous Deliverances already for us: May never any Foreign Forces, or Inteſtine Conſpiracies, prevail againſt him; May ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver any Jealouſies be ſomented between him and his People; May he always think himſelf ſecure in the Hands of his <hi>Engliſh</hi> Subjects, and may they know they are ſo in his. Together with himſelf, May
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:101753:15"/> God bleſs all his Dominions; May they grow in Strength, increaſe in Riches, and excel in Honour; May he keep ſtedfaſt the true Friends to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and baffle the Hopes of thoſe that are not; May he <hi>give Wiſdom to the Wiſe, and ſtop the Mouths of the Fooliſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. As the Conſideration of our own Welfare and Intereſt prompts us to wiſh our ſelves all the Good imaginable, ſo let our Compaſſion ſtir us up to pray for the Relief of our diſtreſſed Brethren the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants abroad: May God, in his due time, as he once did the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> lead this his People through thoſe Red Seas of Blood, through thoſe Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſes of Pains and Troubles, if not into ſome <hi>pleaſant Land</hi> here upon Earth, yet to the <hi>Heavenly Canaan</hi> at laſt: May he give them Conſtancy in their Faith, and Patience under their Sufferings; and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Numbers he is pleas'd to ſuffer to be diminiſh'd from the <hi>Communion of his Saints</hi> here upon Earth, may he add to the <hi>Noble Army of Martyrs</hi> in Heaven.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> Let us pray unto God, that he would look down upon this ſinful People of <hi>England,</hi> and that he would avert thoſe Judgments which, we muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, might be our due Reward.</p>
            <p>But inſtead of Judgments, God has heap'd Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies upon us of late; he has firſt ſav'd us from the Slavery of our Conſciences, and indeed, of our Perſons; next, he has frequently deliver'd us from the Devices of Wicked Men, who have uſed ſeveral Ways and Means to ruin us; ſometimes by endeavouring to take off our King, ſometimes by corrupting our Coin, and by many other Ways, which Reſtleſs Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits are fruitful enough at inventing. And now at
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:101753:15"/> laſt, he has crown'd all his Mercies to us, in the Bleſſing of a Peace: <hi>Thou haſt made Wars to ceaſe amongſt us; thou haſt broke the Bow, and cut the Spear in ſunder,</hi> (as holy <hi>David</hi> ſpeaks.) <hi>Nation ſhall not now lift Sword up againſt Nation; neither ſhall they learn War any more,</hi> ſays the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> of the <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites,</hi> when they repented, and turn'd unto God. May <hi>We</hi> alſo repent, and turn, that we may have the Benefit of this Prophecy too: May this our Peace prove firm and laſting, and may we never again be embroil'd in Wars and Blood. However, I heartily wiſh that the King may never want ſuch Subjects, of ſuch Skill and Courage, ſuch Loyalty and true Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty, to defend him, our Country, and our Church, upon any Occaſion, as his late <hi>Engliſh</hi> Army was. But then, I will crave Leave to add this one Prayer, to end all; and I believe every Soldier that was in the Army, I am ſure every true <hi>Engliſh-Man,</hi> that loves his Country, will join with me; and that is, How neceſſary ſoever an Army may be, in Times of Exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gency, for the Defence of our King, our Country, and our Church, yet God grant that neither of them may ever again have Occaſion to make uſe of their Swords, or to try either their Skill, or their Courage.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
